<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first sermon preached to King Charles, at Saint Iames 3⁰. April. 1625. By Iohn Donne, Deane of Saint Pauls, London.</title>
            <author>Donne, John, 1572-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110043</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900476</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135873</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73848)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2039:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first sermon preached to King Charles, at Saint Iames 3⁰. April. 1625. By Iohn Donne, Deane of Saint Pauls, London.</title>
                  <author>Donne, John, 1572-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A[ugustine]. M[athewes]. for Thomas Iones, and are to bee sold at his shop at the signe of the Blacke Rauen in the Strand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>With two lines of errata on H4r. Variant: with one line of errata.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of "Foure sermons upon speciall occasions" and of "Five sermons upon speciall occasions".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XI, 3 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135873:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135873:1"/>
            <p>THE FIRST SERMON PREACHED TO KING CHARLES, At Saint IAMES: 3<hi rend="sup">0</hi>. April. 1625.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IOHN DONNE, <hi>Deane of</hi> Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> London.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A.M.</hi> for THOMAS IONES, and are to bee ſold at his Shop at the Signe of the Blacke Rauen in the Strand. 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:135873:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135873:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALME. 11.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>If the Foundations be deſtroyed, what can the righteous doe?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee are ſtill in the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Mortification;</hi> in <hi>Lent:</hi> But wee ſearch no longer for <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> The Almightie hand of <hi>God</hi> hath ſhed and ſpred a <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>Mortification</hi> ouer all the land. The laſt <hi>Sabboth</hi> day, was his <hi>Sabboth</hi> who entred then into his euerlaſting <hi>Reſt;</hi> Be this our <hi>Sabboth,</hi> to enter into a holy and thankfull acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that <hi>Rest,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> affords vs, in continuing to vs our <hi>Foundations;</hi> for, <hi>If foundations be deſtroyed, what can the righteous doe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:135873:3"/>I ſcarſe know any word in the Word of <hi>God,</hi> in which the <hi>Originall</hi> is more ambiguous, and conſequently the <hi>Tranſlations</hi> more various, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, neceſſarily alſo, the <hi>Expoſitions</hi> more diuers, then in theſe words. There is one thing, in which all agree, that is, the <hi>Argument,</hi> and <hi>purpoſe,</hi> and <hi>ſcape</hi> of the <hi>Pſalme;</hi> And then, in what ſenſe, the words of the <hi>Text</hi> may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the ſcope of the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> wee reſt in this Tranſlation, which our Church hath accepted and authorized, and which agrees with the firſt Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation knowen to vs, by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that is the <hi>Chalde Paraphraſe, If Foundations bee deſtroyed, what can the righteous doe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>God</hi> euer deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herſelfe in a holy officiouſneſſe in the Commemoration of <hi>Martyrs:</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all their ſolemne, and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Meetings, and Congregations, in the Primitiue Church, were for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135873:3"/>
that, for the honourable Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Martyrs: And for that, they came ſoone to inſtitute and appoynt certaine <hi>Liturgies,</hi> certaine <hi>Offices</hi> (as they called them) certaine <hi>Seruices</hi> in the Church, which ſhould haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to that, to the Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Martyrs;</hi> as wee haue in our Booke of Common Prayer, certaine <hi>Seruices</hi> for <hi>Marriage,</hi> for <hi>Buriall,</hi> and for ſuch other holy Celebrations; And in the Office and Seruice of a <hi>Martyr,</hi> the Church did vſe this <hi>Pſalme;</hi> This <hi>Pſalme,</hi> which is in generall, a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of <hi>Dauid,</hi> That though hee were ſo vehemently purſued by <hi>Saul,</hi> as that all that wiſhed him well, ſayd to his Soule, <hi>Flie as a Bird to the Mountaine,</hi> as it is in the firſt verſe; Though hee ſaw, <hi>That the wicked had bent their Bowes, and made ready their Arrowes, vpon the ſtring, that they might priuily ſhoot at the vpright in heart,</hi> as it is in the ſecond verſe: Though he take
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135873:4"/>
it almoſt as granted, that <hi>Foundations are deſtroyed, (And then, what can the righteous doe?)</hi> as it is in the third verſe which is our <hi>Text,</hi> yet in this diſtreſſe he findes what to doe. For as hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne in the firſt verſe, <hi>In thee Lord, put I my truſt:</hi> So after he had paſſed the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeration of his dangers, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third verſes, in the fourth he purſues it as he begun, <hi>The Lord is in his holy Temple, the Lords Throane is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> And in the fifth hee fixes it thus, <hi>The Lord tryeth the Righteous,</hi> (he may ſuffer much to be done for their triall) <hi>but the wicked, and him that loueth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, his ſoule hateth.</hi> This then is the <hi>Syllogiſme,</hi> this is the <hi>Argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the righteous Man; In Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall things, in Circumſtantiall things, in things that are not fundamentall, a righteous Man, a conſtant Man ſhould not bee ſhaked at all, not at all Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized; Thats true; But then (in a ſecond place) ſometimes it comes to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135873:4"/>
that, <hi>That Foundations are deſtroyd, and what can the Righteous doe then?</hi> Why euen then, this is a queſtion, not of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation, that nothing can bee done, but of Conſultation with God, what ſhould be done. I know, ſayes <hi>Dauid,</hi> I ſhould not be, and thou knoweſt, O God, I haue not beene mou'd with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary trialls; not though my Friends haue diſ-auowed mee, and bid <hi>mee flye to the Mountaine as a Bird,</hi> not though mine enemies prepare, and <hi>prepare Arrowes,</hi> and ſhoote, and <hi>ſhoote priuily,</hi> (beſtowe their labour, and their coſt, and their witts, to ruine mee) yet theſe haue not moou'd mee, becauſe I had fixed my ſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on certaine <hi>Foundations,</hi> Confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Aſſurances of Deliuerance from thee. But if, O Lord, I ſee theſe foundations deſtroyed, if thou put mee into mine Enemies hand, if thou make them thy Sword, if their furie draw that Sword, and then, thy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135873:5"/>
Arme, ſinewed euen with thine owne indignation, ſtrike with that ſword, what can I, how righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſoeuer I were, doe? So then, for the <hi>Explication,</hi> and <hi>Application</hi> of theſe words, there will need no more, but to ſpread them by way of <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> vpon theſe three conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations:<note place="margin">Diuiſio.</note> Firſt, That the righteous is bolde as a <hi>Lyon,</hi> not eaſily ſhaked; But then, <hi>Foundations</hi> themſelues may bee deſtroyed, and ſo hee may bee ſhaked; If hee bee, yet hee knowes what to doe, or where to aske Counſell, for theſe are not wordes of <hi>Desperation,</hi> but of <hi>Conſultation, If Foundations-bee deſtroyed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">part </seg>1</label> Firſt then, wee fixe our ſelues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this conſideration, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in propoſing this thus, <hi>If Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations bee destroyed,</hi> intimates preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantly, that except there bee danger of deſtroying <hi>Foundations,</hi> it is the part of the righteous Man, the godly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135873:5"/>
man to bee quiet. <hi>Studie to bee quiet,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Apoſtle; Studie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.11.</note> that is an a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction of the Minde; and then, <hi>Opo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram detis,</hi> ſay the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgate Edition, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to bee quiet,</hi> and <hi>Labour</hi> is an acti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the bodie: Indeed it is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per buſineſſe of the <hi>Minde</hi> and <hi>Bodie</hi> too, of <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> too, to bee quiet: And yet, alas, how many breake their ſleepe in the night, about things that diſquiet them in the day too, and trouble themſelues in the day, about things that diſquiet them all night too? Wee diſquiet our ſelues too much, in beeing ouer tender, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſenſible of imaginarie iniuries. <hi>Tranſeant iniuriae,</hi> ſayes the Morall man; <hi>Let many iniuries paſſe ouer;</hi> for,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>Plaerasque non accipit, qui neſcit; Hee that knowes not of an iniurie, or takes no knowledge of it, for the moſt part, hath no iniurie. Qui inquirunt, quid in ſe dictum eſt,</hi> ſayes hee, They that are too inquiſitiue, what other men
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135873:6"/>
ſay of them, they diſquiet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; for that which others would but <hi>whisper,</hi> they <hi>publiſh.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which hee addes there, for <hi>Morall,</hi> and <hi>Ciuill</hi> matters, holds in a good proportion, in things of a more <hi>Diuine</hi> Nature, in ſuch parts of the religious worſhip and ſeruice of <hi>God,</hi> as concerne not <hi>Foundations, Non expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit omnia videre, non omnia audire;</hi> we muſt not too iealouſly ſuſpect, not too bitterly condemne, not too peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily conclude, that what ſoeuer is not done, as wee would haue it done, or as wee haue ſeene it done in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, is not well done: for there is a large Latitude, and, by neceſsitie of Circumſtances, much may bee admitted, and yet no <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations deſtroyed;</hi> and till <hi>Foundations bee deſtroyed, the righteous ſhould bee quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this ſhould not prepare, this ſhould not incline any man, to ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135873:6"/>
an indifferencie, as that it ſhould bee all one to him, what became of all things; all one, whether wee had one, or two, or tenne, or no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; or that hee ſhould not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, and actiue, and diligent, in aſsiſting trueth, and reſiſting all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of Errour. For, <hi>God</hi> hath ſayd of all, into whoſe hand hee hath committed power, <hi>You are Gods.</hi> Now, they are not <hi>Gods,</hi> but <hi>Idoles,</hi> if, as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.6.</note> 
               <hi>They haue Eyes and ſee not, Eares and heare not, Hands and ſtrike not;</hi> nay, (as hee addes there) <hi>if they haue Noſes and ſmell not;</hi> if they ſmell not out a miſchieuous practiſe, before it come to execution. For, <hi>Gods eyes are vpon the wayes of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 33.21.</note> 
               <hi>and hee ſees all his goings:</hi> Thoſe, who are in the number of them, of whome <hi>God</hi> hath ſaid, they are <hi>Gods,</hi> muſt haue their eyes vpon the <hi>wayes</hi> of men, and not vpon their <hi>Ends</hi> onely; vpon the <hi>pathes</hi> of miſchiefe, and not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135873:7"/>
vpon the <hi>bed</hi> of miſchiefe onely; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Actors</hi> of miſchiefe, and not vpon the <hi>Act</hi> onely. <hi>Gods eyes ſees our wayes,</hi> ſayes <hi>Dauid</hi> too; that, is, hee can ſee them, when hee will; but there is more in the other <hi>Prophet, Gods eyes are open vpon all our wayes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 32.19.</note> alwayes open, and hee cannot chuſe but ſee: So that, a wilfull ſhutting of the eye, a winking, a conniuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, is not an aſsimilation to <hi>God.</hi> And then,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>Gods eyes are purer, then to beholde euill, and they cannot looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on iniquitie:</hi> So that in an indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, whether Times, or Perſons bee good or badd, there is not this aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation to <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.13.</note> Againe, <hi>All things are naked and open to the eyes of God:</hi> So that in the diſguiſing, and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liating, and extenuating the faults of men, there is not this aſsimilation to <hi>God.</hi> Thus farre they falſifie <hi>Gods</hi> Word, who hath ſayd, <hi>They are Gods;</hi> for <hi>they are Idoles; and not Gods, if they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135873:7"/>
haue eyes, and ſee not.</hi> So is it alſo in the conſideration of the <hi>Eare</hi> too for, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.9.</note> 
               <hi>Shall not hee that planted the Eare, heare?</hi> So wee may ſay, Shall hee upon whom <hi>God</hi> hath planted an Eare, bee deafe? <hi>Gods</hi> eares are ſo open ſo tender, ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of any motion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.12</note> as that <hi>Dauid</hi> formes one Prayer thus, <hi>Auribus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe lachrimas meas,</hi> O Lord, heare my teares, hee puts the office of the <hi>Eye</hi> too, vpon the <hi>Eare.</hi> And then, if the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> ſtop his Eares with <hi>Wooll,</hi> (with ſtaple bribes, profitable bribes) and with <hi>Cyuet</hi> in his wooll, (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes of pleaſure and preferment in his bribes) hee falſifies <hi>Gods</hi> Word, who hath ſaid, they are <hi>Gods,</hi> for <hi>they are Idoles, and not Gods, if they haue eares, and heare not:</hi> And ſo it is alſo of the hand too, In all that <hi>Iob</hi> ſuffered, he ſayes no more, but that <hi>the Hand of God had touched him;</hi> but <hi>touched</hi> him, in reſpect of that hee could haue
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135873:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
done: for, when <hi>Iob</hi> ſayes to men, <hi>Why perſecute you mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 19.22</note> 
               <hi>as God?</hi> hee meanes, as <hi>God</hi> could doe, ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently, ſo ruinouſly, ſo deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely, ſo irreparably. There is no <hi>phraſe</hi> oftner in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> then that <hi>God</hi> deliuered his people, in the <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the <hi>hand</hi> of the <hi>Prophets:</hi> all their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall office is called the <hi>Hand:</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as <hi>Dauid</hi> prayes to <hi>God, That hee would pull his hand out of his boſome, and ſtrike:</hi> ſo muſt wee euer exhort the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> That hee would plucke his hand out of his pocket, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what is there, and execute the Cauſe committed to him. For, as wee, at laſt, ſhall commend our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, into the hands of <hi>God, God</hi> hath commended our Spirits, not onely our ciuill peace, but our Religion too, into the <hi>hand</hi> of the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayes, <hi>Studie to bee quiet,</hi> it is not quiet in the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135873:8"/>
of the <hi>Eye,</hi> nor quiet in the <hi>Deafeneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Eare,</hi> nor quiet in the <hi>Lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of the <hi>Hand;</hi> the iuſt diſcharge of the dueties of our ſeuerall places, is no <hi>diſquieting</hi> to any man. But when <hi>priuate</hi> men will ſpend all their thoughts vpon their <hi>Superiours</hi> acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, this muſt neceſſarily diſquiet them; for they are off of their owne <hi>Center,</hi> and they are <hi>extra Sphaeram Actiuitatis,</hi> out of their owne <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> and <hi>Compaſſe,</hi> and they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſsibly diſcerne the <hi>Ende,</hi> to which their <hi>Superiours</hi> goe. And to ſuch a iealous man, when his iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie is not a tenderneſſe towards his owne actions, which is a holy and a wholeſome iealouſie, but a ſuſpition of his <hi>Superiours</hi> actions, to this Man, euery <hi>Wheele</hi> is a <hi>Drumme,</hi> and euery <hi>Drumme</hi> a <hi>Thunder,</hi> and euery <hi>Thunder-clapp</hi> a diſſolution of the whole frame of the VVorld: If there fall a broken tyle from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135873:9"/>
houſe, hee thinkes <hi>Foundations are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed;</hi> if a crazie woman, or a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient childe, or a needie ſeruant fall from our <hi>Religion,</hi> from our <hi>Church,</hi> hee thinkes the whole <hi>Church</hi> muſt neceſſarily fall, when all this while there are no <hi>Foundations deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and <hi>till foundations bee deſtroyed, the righteous ſhould be quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence haue wee iuſt occaſion, firſt to <hi>condole</hi> amongſt <hi>our ſelues,</hi> who, for matters of <hi>Foundations</hi> profeſſe one and the ſame <hi>Religion,</hi> and then to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of our <hi>Aduerſaries,</hi> who are of another. Firſt, that amongſt our ſelues, for matters not <hi>Doctrinall,</hi> or if <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall,</hi> yet not <hi>Fundamentall,</hi> onely becauſe wee are ſub-diuided in diuers <hi>Names,</hi> there ſhould bee ſuch Exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, ſuch Exacerbations, ſuch Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferations, ſuch Eiulations, ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famations of one another, as if all <hi>Foundations</hi> were deſtroyed. VVho would not tremble, to heare thoſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:135873:9"/>
words, ſpoken by men, to men, of one and the ſame Religion funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, as <hi>Indiabolificata, Perdia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolificata,</hi> and <hi>Superdiabolificata,</hi> that the <hi>Deuill,</hi> and all the <hi>Deuills</hi> in Hell, and worſe then the <hi>Deuill</hi> is in their <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and in their <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> when, <hi>God</hi> in heauen knowes, if their owne vncharitableneſſe did not exclude him, there were roome enough for the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> on both, and on either ſide, in thoſe <hi>Fundamentall</hi> things, which are vnanimely profeſſed by both: And yet euery <hi>Mart,</hi> wee ſee more Bookes written by theſe men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one another, then by them both, for <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet though this <hi>Torrent</hi> of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſſe amongſt them, bee too violent, yet it is within ſome bankes; though it bee a <hi>Sea,</hi> and too tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous, it is limitted within ſome bounds; The poynts are certaine, knowen, limitted, and doe not grow
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135873:10"/>
vpon vs euery yeare, and day. But the vncharitableneſſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> towards vs all, is not a <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> nor it is not a <hi>Sea,</hi> but a <hi>generall Flood,</hi> an vniuerſall <hi>Deluge,</hi> that ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes all the world, but that <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Church-yard,</hi> that <hi>Towne,</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbes,</hi> themſelues, and thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon them; and will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe poſsibilitie of Saluation to the whole <hi>Arke,</hi> the whole <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> but to one <hi>Cabin</hi> in that <hi>Arke,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and then denie vs this Saluation, not for any <hi>Poſitiue</hi> Errour, that euer they charged vs to affirme; not becauſe wee affirme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, that they denie, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee denie ſome things, which they in their afternoone are come to affirme.</p>
            <p>If they were <hi>Iuſti,</hi> Righteous, right and iuſt dealing men, they would not raiſe ſuch duſtes, and then blind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mens eyes with this duſt of their own
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135873:10"/>
rayſing, in things that concerne no <hi>Foundations.</hi> It is true, that all <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> does concerne <hi>Foundations:</hi> there is no <hi>Hereſie</hi> to bee called little: Great <hi>Hereſies</hi> proceeded from things, in apparance, ſmall at firſt, and ſeem'd to looke but towards ſmall matters. There were great <hi>Hereſies,</hi> that were but <hi>Verball, Hereſies</hi> in ſome Word. That great Storme, that ſhaked the <hi>State,</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> in the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and came to Factions, and Commotions in the <hi>Secular</hi> part, and to Exautorations, and Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications amongſt the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſo farre, as that the <hi>Emperour</hi> came to declare both ſides to bee <hi>Heretiques;</hi> All this was for an Errour in a <hi>Word,</hi> in the word <hi>Deipara,</hi> whether the <hi>Bleſſed Virgine Marie</hi> were to bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> or no. There haue beene <hi>Verball Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies</hi> that were but <hi>Syllabicall;</hi> little <hi>Praepoſitions</hi> made <hi>Hereſies;</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135873:11"/>
               <hi>State-praepoſitions,</hi> Precedencies, and Prerogatiues of <hi>Church</hi> aboue <hi>Church,</hi> occaſioned great <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> but <hi>Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Praepoſitions, Praepoſitions</hi> in <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> occaſioned great <hi>Hereſies.</hi> That great <hi>Hereſie</hi> of the <hi>Acephali,</hi> againſt which <hi>Damaſcene</hi> bendes himſelfe in his Booke, <hi>De Natura Compoſita,</hi> was grounded in the <hi>Praepoſition, In;</hi> They would confeſſe <hi>Ex,</hi> but not <hi>In,</hi> That <hi>Chriſt</hi> was made <hi>of</hi> two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but that hee did not conſiſt <hi>in</hi> two Natures. And wee all know, what differences haue beene rayſed in the <hi>Church,</hi> in that one poynt of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> by theſe three Prepoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Trans, Con,</hi> and <hi>Sub.</hi> There haue beene great <hi>Hereſies,</hi> but <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball,</hi> but <hi>Syllabicall;</hi> and as great, but <hi>Litterall;</hi> The greateſt <hi>Hereſie</hi> that euer was, that of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> was but in one Letter. So then, in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,</hi> there is nothing to bee called little, nothing to bee ſuffered. It
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135873:11"/>
was excellently ſayde of <hi>Heretiques,</hi> (though by one, who, though not then declared,<note place="margin">Neſtorius.</note> was then an <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique</hi> in his heart,) <hi>Condolere Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis crimen est;</hi> It is a fault, not onely to bee too indulgent to an <hi>Heretique,</hi> but to bee too compaſsionate of an <hi>Heretique,</hi> too ſorrie for an <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.</hi> It is a fault to ſay, Alas, let him alone, hee is but an <hi>Heretique;</hi> but, to ſay, Alas, hope well of him, till you bee better ſure, that hee is an Heretique, is charitably ſpoken. <hi>God</hi> knowes, the ſharpe and ſowre Name of <hi>Heretique,</hi> was too ſoone let looſe, and too faſt ſpread in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of the world. VVee ſee, that in ſome of the firſt <hi>Catalogues,</hi> that were made of <hi>Heretiques,</hi> men were Regiſtred for <hi>Heretiques,</hi> that had but expounded a place of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> otherwiſe then that place had beene formerly expounded, though there were no harme, in that newe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135873:12"/>
Expoſition. And then, when once that infamous Name of <hi>Heretique</hi> was faſtened vpon a man, nothing was too heauie for, any thing was beleeued of that man. And from thence it is, without queſtion, that wee finde ſo many ſo abſurd, ſo ſenſeleſſe Opinions imputed to thoſe men, who were then called <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques,</hi> as could not, in trueth, with any poſsibilitie, fall into the imagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation or fancie of any man, much leſſe bee <hi>Doctrinally,</hi> or <hi>Dogmatically</hi> deliuered. And then, vpon this, there iſſued <hi>Lawes,</hi> from particular <hi>States,</hi> againſt particular <hi>Hereſies,</hi> that troubled thoſe <hi>States</hi> then, as namely, againſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> or <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians,</hi> and ſuch; and in a ſhort time, theſe <hi>Lawes</hi> came to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, to all ſuch <hi>Opinions,</hi> as the paſsion of ſucceeding times, called <hi>Hereſie.</hi> And at laſt, the <hi>Romane Church</hi> hauing conſtituted that <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polie,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:135873:12"/>
That Shee onely ſhould declare what ſhould bee <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing declared that to bee <hi>Hereſie,</hi> which oppoſed, or retarded the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of <hi>that Church,</hi> now they call in <hi>Brachium Spirituale,</hi> All thoſe Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of <hi>Fathers,</hi> or <hi>Councells</hi> that mention <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and they call in <hi>Brachium Saeculare,</hi> all thoſe <hi>Lawes</hi> which puniſh <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and whereas theſe <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Councells,</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> intended by <hi>Hereſie,</hi> Opinions that deſtroyed <hi>Foundations,</hi> they bend all theſe againſt euery poynt, which may endammage, not the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> nor the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> nor the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the <hi>Kitchin</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> not for the <hi>Heart,</hi> but for the <hi>Bellie;</hi> not the <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> but the <hi>Policie;</hi> not the <hi>Altar,</hi> but the <hi>Exchequer</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Righteous lookes to <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations,</hi> before hee will bee ſcandalized
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135873:13"/>
himſelfe, or condemne another. When they call Saint <hi>Peter</hi> their firſt <hi>Pope,</hi> and being remembred, how hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied his <hi>Maſter,</hi> ſay then, that was but an Acte of <hi>Infirmitie,</hi> not of <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie,</hi> and there were no <hi>Foundations</hi> deſtroyed in that; wee preſſe not that euidence againſt <hi>Saint Peter,</hi> wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, and wee are quiet. When wee charge ſome of <hi>Saint Peters</hi> imaginary Succeſſors, ſome of their <hi>Popes,</hi> with actuall, and perſonall <hi>Sacrificing</hi> to <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles,</hi> ſome with <hi>ſubſcribing</hi> to formall <hi>Hereſies,</hi> with their owne hand, many with ſo enormous an ill life, as that their owne Authors will ſay, that for many yeares together, there liued not one <hi>Pope,</hi> of whoſe Saluation, any hope could bee conceiued; and they anſwere to all this, that all theſe were but <hi>Perſonall</hi> faults, and deſtroyed no <hi>Foundations;</hi> wee can bee content to bury their faultes with their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and wee are quiet. When wee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135873:13"/>
remember them, how many of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> excuſed <hi>officious Lyes,</hi> and thought ſome kinde of <hi>Lying</hi> to bee no <hi>Sinne,</hi> how very many of them hearded in the <hi>hereſie</hi> of the <hi>Millenarians,</hi> That the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ſhould enioy a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares of temporall felicity in this world, after their <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> before they aſcended into Heauen; And that they ſay to all this, The <hi>Fathers</hi> ſaid theſe things before the <hi>Church</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed any thing to the contrary, and till that, it was lawfull for any man to ſay, or thinke what hee would, wee do not load the memory of thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Fathers</hi> with any heauier preſsings, but wee are quiet. Yet wee cannot chuſe but tell them, that tell vs this, that they haue taken a hard way, to make that ſaying true, that all things are growen deare in our times; for they haue made <hi>Saluation</hi> deare; Threeſcore yeares agoe, a man might haue beene ſau'd at halfe the price hee can now:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135873:14"/>
Threeſcore yeares agoe, he might haue beene ſaued for beleeuing the <hi>Apoſtles Creed;</hi> now it will coſt him the <hi>Trent Creed</hi> too. Euermore they will preſſe for all, and yeeld nothing; and there is indeed their <hi>Specification,</hi> there's their <hi>Character,</hi> that's their <hi>Catholique,</hi> their <hi>Vniuerſall;</hi> To <hi>haue all;</hi> As, in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his time, when the <hi>Emperour</hi> preſſed him to affoord the <hi>Arrians</hi> one <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where hee was <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and hee asked but one <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> where the <hi>Arrians</hi> preuayled, not doubting but hee ſhould draw more to the true <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Antioch,</hi> then they ſhould corrupt in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> yet this would not bee granted; It would not be granted at <hi>Rome,</hi> if we ſhould aske a <hi>Church</hi> for a <hi>Church.</hi> In a word, wee charge them with <hi>vncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> (and <hi>Charitie</hi> is without all Controuerſie, a <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) that they will ſo peremptorily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude vs from Heauen, for matters
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135873:14"/>
that doe not appertaine to <hi>Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> For, if they will call all <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> that that <hi>Church hath,</hi> or <hi>doth,</hi> or <hi>ſhall</hi> decree, wee muſt learne our <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme</hi> vpon our <hi>Death-bedd,</hi> and inquire for the Articles of our Faith, when wee are going out of the world, for they may haue decreed ſomething that Morning. No one <hi>Author</hi> of theirs denied <hi>Pope Ioane,</hi> till they diſcerned the <hi>Conſequence,</hi> That by confeſsing a <hi>Woman Pope,</hi> they ſhould diſparage that <hi>Succeſsion</hi> of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> which they pretend, And this <hi>Succeſsion</hi> muſt bee <hi>Foundation.</hi> No Author of our ſide denied <hi>Saint Peters</hi> beeing at <hi>Rome,</hi> till wee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the <hi>Conſequence,</hi> That vpon his <hi>perſonall</hi> being there, they grounded a <hi>Primacie</hi> in that <hi>Sea,</hi> And this <hi>Primacie</hi> muſt bee <hi>Foundation.</hi> Much might bee admitted in caſes of <hi>In differencie,</hi> euen in the <hi>Nature of the things,</hi> Much in caſes of <hi>Neceſsitie,</hi> for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135873:15"/>
the <hi>importance of Circumſtances,</hi> much in caſes of <hi>Conueniency,</hi> for the ſuppling of boyſterous, and for the becalming of tempeſtuous humours; but when eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing muſt be called <hi>Foundation,</hi> we ſhall neuer knowe where to ſtop, where to conſiſt. If wee ſhould beleeue their <hi>Sacrificium incruentum,</hi> their vnbloody Sacrifice in the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> if wee did not beleeue their <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium Cruentum</hi> too, that there was a power in that <hi>Church,</hi> to ſacrifice the Blood of <hi>Kings,</hi> wee ſhould bee ſayde to bee defectiue in a <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Article.</hi> If wee ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt their <hi>Metaphyſiques,</hi> their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt their <hi>Chimiques,</hi> their <hi>Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> Fires, and their <hi>Mythologie,</hi> and <hi>Poetrie,</hi> their apparitions of <hi>Soules</hi> and <hi>Spirits,</hi> they would binde vs to their <hi>Mathematiques</hi> too, and they would not let vs bee ſaued, except wee would reforme our <hi>Almanackes</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:135873:15"/>
to their <hi>tenne dayes,</hi> and reforme our <hi>Clockes</hi> to their <hi>foure and twentie:</hi> for who can tell when there is an ende of <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> in an <hi>Arbitrarie,</hi> and in an <hi>Occaſionall Religion?</hi> When then this <hi>Prophet</hi> ſayes, <hi>If Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bee deſtroyed, what can the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doe,</hi> hee meanes, that till that, the righteous ſhould bee <hi>quiet:</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were in <hi>fundamentall Articles</hi> of Faith, our ſelues ſhould not bee ſo bitter towards one another, our Aduerſarie ſhould not bee ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable againſt vs all. And farther wee need not extend this firſt Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, to Suruay ſome <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">part </seg>2</label> ſuch <hi>Foundations,</hi> as fall within the frayltie, and ſuſpition, and poſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of this Text, that they may bee deſtroyed: for when the Prophet ſayes, <hi>If they bee,</hi> they may bee. Now <hi>Fundamentum proprie de aedificijs dicitur,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Lawe:</hi> when wee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135873:16"/>
ſpeake of <hi>Foundations,</hi> wee intend a <hi>houſe:</hi> and heere, wee extend this <hi>Houſe</hi> to foure Conſiderations; for in foure <hi>Houſes</hi> haue euery one of vs a dwelling. For, firſt, <hi>Eccleſia Domus,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> is a <hi>Houſe,</hi> it is <hi>Gods houſe;</hi> and in that Houſe, wee are <hi>of the houſeholde of the faithfull,</hi> if (as it is teſtified of <hi>Moſes) wee bee faithfull in all his Houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>as Seruants.</hi> You ſee there is a faithfulneſſe required in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man, in <hi>all the houſe of God,</hi> not in any one roome; a diſpoſition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to doe good to the whole <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God</hi> euery where, and not onely at <hi>home.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Respublica Domus,</hi> The <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> the <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> is a <hi>Houſe;</hi> and this is that which is called ſo often, <hi>Domus Iſrael, The houſe of Iſrael,</hi> the State, the Gouernment of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> And in this <hi>Houſe, God</hi> dwells, as well as in the other; In the <hi>State,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Church:</hi> For, theſe words, <hi>The
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135873:16"/>
Lord hath choſen Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 132.13</note> 
               <hi>hee hath deſired it for a habitation,</hi> are ſpoken of the whole Bodie, <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> Thirdly, there is <hi>Domus Habitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Domus quae Domicilium,</hi> a Houſe to dwell in, and to dwell with, a <hi>Family:</hi> and in this Houſe <hi>God</hi> dwells too; for, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayes of the <hi>Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> wee may ſay of the <hi>Dwelling, Except the Lord build the Houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.1.</note> 
               <hi>they labour in vaine:</hi> So except the Lord dwell in the Houſe, it is a deſolate Habitation. And then laſtly, there is <hi>Domus quae Dominus,</hi> a houſe which is the <hi>Master</hi> of the <hi>Houſe;</hi> for as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Man is a little World, ſo eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man is his owne Houſe, and dwels in himſelfe: And in this <hi>Houſe God</hi> dwells too; for the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſeemes ſo much to delight himſelfe in that <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphore,</hi> as that hee repeats it almoſt in all his <hi>Epiſtles, Habitat in nobis,</hi> That the Holy Ghoſt dwells in vs. Now, of all theſe foure <hi>Houſes,</hi> that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135873:17"/>
               <hi>houſe</hi> which hath no walles, but is ſpread ouer the face of the whole Earth, the <hi>Church,</hi> And that <hi>Houſe,</hi> which with vs, hath no other walls, but the <hi>Sea,</hi> the <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> And that <hi>houſe</hi> which is walled with <hi>drie Earth,</hi> our dwelling houſe, our family, and this <hi>houſe</hi> which is wall'd with <hi>wet Earth,</hi> this loame of fleſh, our ſelfe, Of all theſe foure houſes, thoſe three, of which, and in which we are, and this fourth, which wee our ſelfe are, <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Foundation,</hi> and ſo <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi> cannot bee deſtroyed; But, as, though the common foundation of all buildings bee the <hi>Earth,</hi> yet wee make particular foundations for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Buildings, of Stone, or Brick, or Piles, as the Soyle requires; ſo ſhall wee alſo heere conſider ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Foundations of theſe foure houſes, as may fall within the frailtie, and ſuſpition, within the poſsibilitie, and danger of the Text, of being <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:135873:17"/>Of the firſt <hi>Houſe</hi> then,<note place="margin">Eccleſia Domus.</note> which is the <hi>Church,</hi> the foundation is <hi>Chriſt, Other foundation can no man lay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>then that which is layd, which is Ieſus Chriſt. Non propterea dicimus,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Augustine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De vnita. Eccleſ. C. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Wee doe not ſay that our <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>Catholique</hi> therefore, becauſe <hi>Optatus</hi> ſayes ſo, and becauſe <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayes ſo, (and yet <hi>Optatus,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the <hi>Fathers,</hi> are good Witneſſes) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we ſay it, (ſayes he) <hi>Quia Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garum noſtrorum Conciliis praedicata eſt,</hi> Becauſe ſome <hi>Synodes</hi> and <hi>Councells</hi> of men of our owne Religion haue ſaid it is <hi>Catholique</hi> (And yet a <hi>Harmony of Confeſsions</hi> is good Euidence,) <hi>Nec quia tanta fiunt in ea mirabilia,</hi> ſayes hee, wee call it not <hi>Catholique,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo many <hi>Myracles</hi> are wrought in it, (for wee oppoſe <hi>Gods</hi> many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Deliuerances of this <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> to all their <hi>imaginary mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> of <hi>Rome) Non ideo manifeſtatur Catholica,</hi> ſayes ſtill that <hi>Father,</hi> All
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135873:18"/>
this does not make our Church <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique,</hi> nay, <hi>non manifeſtatur,</hi> all this does not declare it to bee <hi>Catholique,</hi> all theſe are no infallible marks there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but onely this one, ſayes hee, <hi>Quia ipſe Dominus Ieſus, &amp;c.</hi> becauſe the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> himſelfe is the <hi>Foundation</hi> of this Church. But may not this be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to reaſoning, to various Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Whether wee haue that <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or no? It may; but that will goe farre in the clearing thereof, which the ſame Father ſayes in another Booke,<note place="margin">De Moribus Eccleſ. Cat. C. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nihil in Eccleſia catholica ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubrius fit, quam vt Rationem praecedat Autoritas:</hi> Nothing is ſafer for the finding of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Church, then to preferre <hi>Authoritie</hi> before my <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> to ſubmit and captiuate my <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to <hi>Authoritie.</hi> This the <hi>Romane Church</hi> pretends to embrace; but <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly;</hi> like an <hi>Ape,</hi> it kills with embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing; for it euacuates the right <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie;</hi> The <hi>Authority</hi> that they obtrude,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135873:18"/>
is the <hi>Decretals</hi> of their owne <hi>Biſhops,</hi> The <hi>authoritie,</hi> which <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> literally and expreſſely declares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to meane, is the <hi>authoritie</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> then, that is, the <hi>Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> is the <hi>foundation</hi> of this firſt <hi>Houſe,</hi> the <hi>Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Haec ſunt funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta quae iecit Salomon,</hi> ſayes the <hi>vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Edition,</hi> Theſe are the <hi>foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> that <hi>Salomon</hi> layde; and then our <hi>Tranſlation</hi> hath it, <hi>Theſe are the things in which Salomon was instructed;</hi> One calls it <hi>Foundations,</hi> the other <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions;</hi> All's one; The <hi>Inſtructions</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are the <hi>Foundation</hi> of this <hi>Houſe.</hi> For, when the Apoſtle ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Ieſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is the chiefe corner Stone,</hi> yet hee addes there, <hi>Yee are built vpon the Prophets and Apoſtles:</hi> for the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> had their part in the <hi>foundation;</hi> in the <hi>laying,</hi> though
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135873:19"/>
not in the <hi>beeing</hi> of the <hi>Foundation. The wall of the citie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.14</note> ſayes Saint <hi>Iohn, had twelue Foundations, and in them, the Names of the twelue Apoſtles:</hi> But ſtill, in that place, they are <hi>Apoſtles of the Lambe,</hi> ſtill they haue relation to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> For, they, who by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> writt of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo made vp the Bodie of the Scriptures, haue their parts too, in this <hi>Foundation.</hi> Beſides theſe, it is ſayd, in the building of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>The King commaunded, and they brought, great Stones, and coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Stones, and hewed Stones, to lay the foundations of the Houſe:</hi> The care of the <hi>King,</hi> the labours of men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the <hi>foundation.</hi> And beſides this, in that place of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> The <hi>foundation</hi> of the Wall, is ſayde to bee <hi>garniſhed with all manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones; Garniſhed,</hi> but not <hi>made</hi> of that kinde of precious ſtones. So then <hi>Salomons</hi> hewed Stones, and coſtly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135873:19"/>
ſtones, may, in a faire accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, bee vnderſtood to bee the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations,</hi> and <hi>Reſolutions, Canons,</hi> and <hi>Decrees</hi> of generall <hi>Councels:</hi> And Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> garniſhment of precious ſtones, may, in a faire accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, bee vnderſtood to bee the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Laborious, the zealous and the pious <hi>Commentaries</hi> and <hi>Expoſitions</hi> of the <hi>Fathers;</hi> For <hi>Councells</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> aſsiſt the <hi>Foundation;</hi> But the <hi>foundation</hi> it ſelfe is Chriſt himſelfe in his <hi>Word;</hi> his <hi>Scriptures.</hi> And then, certainely they loue the <hi>Houſe</hi> beſt, that loue the <hi>foundation</hi> beſt: not they, that impute to the <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſuch an <hi>Obſcuritie,</hi> as ſhould make them <hi>in-intelligible</hi> to vs, or ſuch a defect as ſhould make them <hi>inſufficient</hi> in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. To denie vs the vſe of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> in our vulgar Tranſlations, and yet to denie vs the vſe of them, in the <hi>Originall</hi> Tongues too, To tell vs we muſt not trie <hi>Controuerſies</hi> by our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135873:20"/>
               <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or our <hi>Latine Bibles,</hi> nor by the <hi>Hebrew Bibles</hi> neither, To put ſuch a Maieſtie vpon the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as that a Lay man may not touch them, and yet to put ſuch a diminution vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as that the writings of men ſhall bee equall to them; this is a wrinching, a ſhrinking, a ſinking, an vndermining, a deſtroying of <hi>Foundations,</hi> of the <hi>foundation</hi> of this firſt <hi>Houſe,</hi> which is the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reſpub. Domus.</note>Enter wee now into a Suruay of the ſecond <hi>Houſe,</hi> The <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> and of this <hi>Houſe,</hi> the <hi>foundation</hi> is the <hi>Law.</hi> And therefore Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> referres this Text, in a litterall and primary ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to that, to the <hi>Law:</hi> for ſo, in his <hi>Commentaries</hi> vpon the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> he tranſlates this Text, <hi>Si diſsipatae Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> Hee makes the euacuating of the <hi>Law,</hi> this deſtroying of <hi>foundations. Lex communis Reipub. ſponſio,</hi> ſayes the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135873:20"/>
               <hi>Law</hi> it ſelfe: The <hi>Law</hi> is the mutuall, the reciprocall Suretie betweene the <hi>State</hi> and the <hi>Subiect.</hi> The <hi>Lawe</hi> is my <hi>Suretie</hi> to the <hi>State,</hi> that I ſhall pay my Obedience, And the <hi>Lawe</hi> is the States <hi>Suretie</hi> to mee, that I ſhall enioy my Protection. And therefore, therein did the <hi>Iewes</hi> iuſtly exalt themſelues aboue all other Nations, That <hi>God was come ſo much nearer to them then to other Nations, by how much they had Lawes and Ordinances more righteous then other Nations had.</hi> Now, as it is ſayd of the <hi>Foundations</hi> of the other <hi>Houſe,</hi> the <hi>Temple, The King commaunded in the laying thereof,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> had his hand in the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo is it alſo in this <hi>Houſe,</hi> the <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> hath his hand <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>vpon</hi> the <hi>foundation</hi> here alſo, which is the <hi>Lawe:</hi> ſo farre, as that euery <hi>forbearing</hi> of a <hi>Lawe,</hi> is not an <hi>Euacuating</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> euery <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> whether a <hi>Poſt-pardon,</hi> by way
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135873:21"/>
of mercy, after a Lawe is broken, or a <hi>Prae-pardon,</hi> by way of <hi>Dispenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in wiſedome before a Lawe bee broken, is not a <hi>Deſtroying of this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> For, when ſuch things as theſe are done,<note place="margin">Iuo.</note> 
               <hi>Non aſtu Mentientis, ſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu compatientis,</hi> not vpon coloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſguiſes, nor priuate reſpects, but truely for the <hi>Generall good,</hi> all theſe <hi>Pardons,</hi> and <hi>Dispenſations</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and concurre to the <hi>Office,</hi> and contract the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Foundation</hi> it ſelfe, which is, that the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die may bee the better ſupported. But where there is an inducing of a <hi>ſuper-Soueraigne,</hi> and a <hi>ſuper-Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie,</hi> and a <hi>Sea</hi> aboue our <hi>foure Seas,</hi> and a <hi>Horne</hi> aboue our <hi>Head,</hi> and a <hi>forraine Power</hi> aboue our <hi>Natiue</hi> and <hi>naturall Power,</hi> where there are dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall, Poſitiue Aſſertions, that men borne of vs, and liuing with vs, and by vs, are yet none of vs, no <hi>Subiects,</hi> owe no <hi>Allegeance,</hi> this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135873:21"/>
is a wrinching, a ſhrinking, a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, an vndermining, a deſtroying of <hi>Foundations,</hi> the <hi>Foundation</hi> of this ſecond <hi>Houſe,</hi> which is the <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third <hi>Houſe</hi> that falles into our preſent Suruay,<note place="margin">Domus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micilium.</note> is <hi>Domus quae Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micilium, Domus habitationis,</hi> our <hi>Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſe,</hi> or <hi>Family,</hi> and of this <hi>houſe,</hi> the <hi>foundation</hi> is <hi>Peace:</hi> for <hi>Peace</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts all the peeces of a <hi>family</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Husband and Wife, in Loue and in Obedience, Father and Sonne, in Care and in Obedience, Maſter and Seruant, in Diſcipline and in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: Still <hi>Obedience</hi> is one Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in all <hi>Peace;</hi> there is no <hi>Peace,</hi> where there is no <hi>Obedience.</hi> Now euery ſmoke does not argue the houſe to bee on fire; Euery domeſtique of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence taken or giuen, does not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this <hi>Foundation,</hi> this <hi>Peace,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doores. There may bee a <hi>Thunder</hi> from aboue, and there may bee an
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135873:22"/>
               <hi>Earth-quake</hi> from below, and yet the <hi>foundation</hi> of the Houſe ſafe: From a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue there may bee a defect in the <hi>Superiour,</hi> in the Husband, the Father, the Maſter; and from below, in the Wife, the Sonne, the Seruant; There may bee a <hi>Iealouſie</hi> in the Husband, a <hi>Moroſitie</hi> in the Father, an <hi>Imperiouſneſſe</hi> in the Maſter; And there may bee an <hi>inobſequiouſneſſe</hi> and an <hi>indiligence</hi> in the Wife, there may bee <hi>leuitie</hi> and <hi>inconſideration</hi> in the Sonne, and there may bee <hi>vnreadineſſe, vnſeaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in a Seruant, and yet <hi>Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſtand, and <hi>Peace</hi> maintayned, though not by an exquiſite perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of all duties, yet by a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſupport of one anothers infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. This deſtroyes no <hi>Foundation;</hi> But if there bee a windowe opened in the houſe, to let in a <hi>Ieſuiticall firebrand,</hi> that ſhall whiſper, though not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime, deliuer with a <hi>non Dominus ſed Ego,</hi> that though it bee not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135873:22"/>
               <hi>Tenet</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> yet hee thinkes, that in caſe of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and Naturall, and Matrimoniall duties ceaſe, no Ciuill, no Naturall, no Matrimoniall Tribute due to an <hi>Heretique;</hi> Or if there bee ſuch a fire kindled within doores, that the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands iealouſie come to a <hi>Subſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of neceſſary meanes at home, or to <hi>Defamation</hi> abroad, or the Wiues leuitie induce iuſt <hi>Imputation</hi> at home, or <hi>ſcandall</hi> abroad, If the Fathers waſtfulneſſe amount to a <hi>Diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> becauſe hee leaues nothing to bee inherited, Or the Sonnes incorrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe occaſion a iuſt <hi>diſinheriting,</hi> though there bee enough, If the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter make <hi>Slaues</hi> of Seruants, and macerate them, or the Seruants make <hi>prize</hi> of the Maſter, and prey vpon him, in theſe caſes, and ſuch as theſe, there is a wrinching, a ſhrinking, a ſinking, an vnderming, a deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Foundations,</hi> the <hi>Foundation</hi> of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135873:23"/>
this third <hi>Houſe,</hi> which is the <hi>family, Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Domus Dominus.</note>There remaines yet another <hi>Houſe,</hi> a fourth Houſe, a poore and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>Cottage;</hi> worſe then our <hi>Statute Cottages;</hi> for to them the <hi>Statute</hi> layes out certaine <hi>Acres;</hi> but for theſe <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages,</hi> wee meaſure not by <hi>Acres,</hi> but by <hi>Feete;</hi> and fiue or ſixe foote ſerues any <hi>Cottager:</hi> ſo much as makes a <hi>Graue,</hi> makes vp the beſt of our <hi>Glebe,</hi> that are of the <hi>Inferiour,</hi> and the beſt of their <hi>Temporalties,</hi> that are of the <hi>Superiour Cleargie,</hi> and the beſt of their <hi>Demeanes</hi> that are in the greateſt <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie</hi> in this world: for this <hi>houſe</hi> is but <hi>our ſelfe,</hi> and the <hi>foundation</hi> of this <hi>Houſe</hi> is <hi>Conſcience.</hi> For, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding with a good <hi>Conſcience</hi> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular action, is that, which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calles,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>The laying vp in ſtore for our ſelues, a good foundation, againſt the time to come:</hi> The <hi>Houſe</hi> comes not till the time to come, but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135873:23"/>
the <hi>Foundation</hi> muſt bee layde heere. <hi>Abraham looked for a Citie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10</note> that was a <hi>future</hi> expectation; but, ſayes that Text, it was a <hi>Citie that hath a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation;</hi> the <hi>foundation</hi> was layd alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, euen in this life, in a good <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> For no intereſt, no manſion ſhall that Man haue in the vpper-roomes of that <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that hath not layd the <hi>foundation</hi> in a good <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> heere. But what is <hi>Conſcience? Conſcience</hi> hath but theſe two <hi>Elements, Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Practiſe;</hi> for <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia preſumit Scientiam;</hi> Hee that does any thing with a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> knowes that hee ſhould doe it, and why hee does it: Hee that does <hi>good</hi> ignorantly, ſtupidly, inconſiderately, implicitely, does <hi>good,</hi> but hee does that good <hi>ill. Conſcience</hi> is, <hi>Syllogiſmus practicus;</hi> vpon certaine premiſſes, well debated, I conclude, that I ſhould doe it, and then I doe it. Now for the deſtroying of this <hi>foundation,</hi> there are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135873:24"/>
               <hi>ſinnes,</hi> which by <hi>Gods</hi> ordinary grace exhibited in his <hi>Church,</hi> prooue but <hi>Alarums,</hi> but <hi>Sentinells</hi> to the <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> The very ſinne, or ſomething that does naturally accompany that ſinne, <hi>Pouertie,</hi> or <hi>Sickeneſſe,</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie,</hi> calls vpon a man, and awakens him to a remorſe of the ſinne. Which made Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſay, <hi>That a man got by ſome ſinnes;</hi> ſome ſinnes helpe him in the way of repentance for ſinne; and theſe ſinnes doe not <hi>deſtroy the foundation.</hi> But there are ſinnes, which in their nature preclude repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp; batter the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> deuaſtate, depopulate, exterminate, annihilate the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and leaue no ſenſe at all, or but a ſenſe of <hi>Deſperation.</hi> And then, the caſe being reduc'd to that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 17.11.</note> 
               <hi>That wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes condemned by her owne wickednes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes very timerous,</hi> (ſo as the <hi>Conſcience</hi> growes afrayd, that the promiſes of the <hi>Gospell</hi> belong not to her) And (as it is added there) <hi>beeing preſſed with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135873:24"/>
Conſcience, alwayes forecaſteth grieuous things</hi>) that whatſoeuer <hi>God</hi> layes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him heere, all that is but his <hi>earneſt</hi> of future worſe torments, when it comes to ſuch a <hi>Feare,</hi> as (as it is added in the next verſe) <hi>Betrayes the ſuccours that Reaſon offers him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 12.</note> That whereas in reaſon a man might argue, <hi>God</hi> hath pardoned greater ſinnes, and greater ſinners, yet hee can finde no hope for himſelfe; this is a ſhrinking, a ſinking, an vndermining, a deſtroying of this <hi>Foundation</hi> of this fourth <hi>Houſe,</hi> the <hi>Conſcience:</hi> And farther wee proceed not in this <hi>Suruay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee are now vpon that which we <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">part </seg>3</label> propoſed for our laſt Conſideration; Till <hi>foundations</hi> are ſhaked, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtirres not; In ſome caſes ſome <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi> may be ſhaked; if they be, <hi>what can the righteous doe?</hi> The <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer askes the queſtion, what the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous,</hi> the wicked can doe: They doe well enough, beſt of all, in ſuch
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135873:25"/>
caſes: Demolitions and Ruines are their raiſings; Troubles are their peace, Tempeſts are their calmes, Fires and combuſtions are their refreſhings, Maſſacres are their harueſt, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is their Vintage; All their Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers runne in Eddies, and all their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are in wheeles, and in perpetuall motions; the wicked do well enough, beſt of all then; <hi>but what ſhall the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous do?</hi> The firſt entrance of the <hi>Pſalme</hi> in the firſt verſe, ſeemes to giue an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere; <hi>The righteous may flie to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as a Bird;</hi> he may <hi>retire,</hi> withdraw himſelfe. But then the generall <hi>ſcope</hi> of the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> giues a <hi>Reply</hi> to the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere;</hi> for all <hi>Expoſitors</hi> take the whole <hi>Pſalme</hi> to bee an anſwere from <hi>Dauid,</hi> and giuen with ſome indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, who perſwaded him to flie, or retire himſelfe. Not that <hi>Dauid</hi> would conſtitute a <hi>Rule</hi> in his <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> that it was vnlawfull to flie in a time of danger or perſecution, (for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135873:25"/>
it would not bee hard to obſerue at leaſt nine or ten ſeuerall flights of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>) but that in ſome caſes ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> and <hi>Perſon,</hi> may accompany and inueſt the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that it may bee inconuenient for <hi>that Man,</hi> at <hi>that Time,</hi> to retire himſelfe. As oft, as the retyring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to the <hi>forſaking of a Calling,</hi> it will become a very diſputable thing, how farre a retyring may bee lawfull. Saint <hi>Peters</hi> vehement zeale in diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Chriſt</hi> from going vp to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.21.</note> in a time of danger, was ſo farre from retarding <hi>Chriſt</hi> in that purpoſe, as that it drew a more bitter increpation from <hi>Chriſt</hi> vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> then at any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time.</p>
            <p>So then, in the <hi>Text,</hi> we haue a <hi>Rule</hi> implyed, <hi>Something is left to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to doe, though ſome Foundations bee deſtroyed;</hi> for the words are words of <hi>Conſultation,</hi> and <hi>conſultation</hi> with <hi>God;</hi> when Man can afford no Counſayle,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135873:26"/>
               <hi>God</hi> can, and will direct thoſe that are his, the righteous, what to doe. The words giue vs the <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> giues vs the <hi>Example</hi> in himſelfe. Firſt, hee continues his <hi>Innocencie,</hi> and <hi>auowes</hi> that; the deſtroying of <hi>Foundations,</hi> does not deſtroy his <hi>Foundation, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence:</hi> ſtill hee is able to confound his aduerſaries,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.46.</note> with that, <hi>Which of you can conuince mee of ſinne?</hi> And then, hee <hi>prayes</hi> for the remoouing of the perſecution, <hi>Tranſeat Calix,</hi> let this Cup paſſe. When that might not bee, hee <hi>prayes</hi> euen for them, who inflicted this perſecution, <hi>Pater ignoſce,</hi> Father forgiue them; And when all is done, hee <hi>ſuffers</hi> all that can bee done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: And hee calls his whole Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Horam ſuam,</hi> it ſpent <hi>nights</hi> and <hi>dayes;</hi> his whole life was a continuall Paſsion; yet how long ſoeuer, he calls it but an <hi>Houre,</hi> and how much ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it were <hi>their</hi> act, the act of their malignitie that did it, yet hee calls it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135873:26"/>
               <hi>his,</hi> becauſe it was the act of his owne <hi>Predestination</hi> as <hi>God,</hi> vpon himſelfe as <hi>Man;</hi> And hee calles it by a more acceptable Name then that, hee calles his Paſsion <hi>Calicem ſuum,</hi> his Cup, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee brought not onely a patience to it, but a delight and a ioy in it; for, <hi>for the ioy that was ſet before him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>hee endured the Croſſe.</hi> All this then the righteous can doe, though <hi>Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bee destroyed;</hi> Hee can <hi>withdrawe</hi> himſelfe, if the duties of his place make not his reſidence neceſſarie; If it doe, hee can <hi>pray;</hi> and then hee can <hi>ſuffer;</hi> and then hee can <hi>reioyce</hi> in his ſufferings; and hee can make that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, Our God is able to deliuer vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>and hee will deliuer vs; but if not, wee will ſerue no other Gods.</hi> For, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous hath euermore this refuge, this aſſurance, that though ſome <hi>Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> bee deſtroyed, all cannot bee: for firſt, <hi>The foundation of God ſtands ſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19</note> 
               <hi>and hee knowes who are his;</hi> Hee is ſafe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135873:27"/>
in <hi>God;</hi> and then he is ſafe in his owne <hi>Conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.25.</note> for, <hi>The Righteous is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting foundation;</hi> not onely that he <hi>hath</hi> one, but <hi>is</hi> one; and not a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary, but an euerlaſting <hi>Foundation:</hi> So that <hi>foundations</hi> can neuer bee ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, but that hee is ſafe in <hi>God,</hi> and ſafe in <hi>himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Domus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia.</note>For ſuch things then, as concerne the <hi>foundation</hi> of the firſt <hi>Houſe,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> Bee not apt to call <hi>Super-Edifications, Foundations;</hi> Collaterall Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, Fundamentall Diuinitie; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blematicall, Diſputable, Controuerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble poynts, poynts Eſſentiall, and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith. Call not <hi>Super-Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Foundations,</hi> nor call not the <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture</hi> of the <hi>Houſe, Foundations;</hi> Call not <hi>Ceremoniall,</hi> and <hi>Rituall</hi> things, <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſentiall</hi> parts of Religion, and of the worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> otherwiſe then as they imply <hi>Diſobedience;</hi> for <hi>Obedience</hi> to lawfull Authoritie, is alwayes an <hi>Eſſentiall</hi> part of Religion. Doe not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135873:27"/>
               <hi>Anti-date</hi> Miſerie; doe not <hi>Propheſie</hi> Ruine; doe not <hi>Concurre</hi> with Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, nor <hi>Contribute</hi> to Miſchiefe ſo farre, as to <hi>ouer-feare</hi> it before, nor to miſ interprete their <hi>wayes,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ends</hi> you cannot knowe; And doe not call the cracking of a pane of glaſſe, a <hi>Deſtroying of foundations.</hi> But euery man doing the particular duties of his diſtinct Calling, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of <hi>Foundations, Praying,</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>Doing,</hi> and <hi>Counſailing,</hi> and <hi>Contributing</hi> too, <hi>Foundations</hi> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neuer deſtroyed, the Righteous ſhall doe ſtill, as they haue done, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy <hi>God</hi> manifeſted in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> applyed in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which is the <hi>foundation</hi> of the firſt <hi>Houſe,</hi> the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For things concerning the <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the ſecond <hi>Houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reſpub. Domus.</note> the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> which is the <hi>Lawe,</hi> Diſpute not <hi>Lawes,</hi> but obey them when they are made; In thoſe <hi>Councells,</hi> where
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135873:28"/>
               <hi>Lawes</hi> are made, or reformed, diſpute; but there alſo, without particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, without priuate affection, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perſonall relations. Call not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery entrance of ſuch a <hi>Iudge,</hi> as thou thinkeſt inſufficient, a <hi>corrupt</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance; nor euery <hi>Iudgement,</hi> which hee enters, and thou vnderſtandeſt not, or likeſt not, a <hi>corrupt</hi> Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. As in <hi>Naturall</hi> things, it is a weakeneſſe to thinke, that euery thing that I knowe not how it is done, is done by <hi>Witch craft,</hi> So is it alſo in <hi>Ciuill</hi> things, if I know not why it is done, to thinke it is done for <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</hi> Let the <hi>Law</hi> bee ſacred to thee, and the Diſpenſers of the <hi>Law,</hi> reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend; Keepe the <hi>Lawe,</hi> and the <hi>Lawe</hi> ſhall keepe thee; And ſo <hi>Foundations</hi> being neuer deſtroyed, the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall doe ſtill, as they haue done, enioy their Poſſeſsions, and Honours, and themſelues, by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſhadowing of the <hi>Lawe,</hi> which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135873:28"/>
is the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the ſecond <hi>Houſe,</hi> the <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For thoſe things which concerne the <hi>Foundations</hi> of the third <hi>Houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Domus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micilium.</note> the <hi>Family,</hi> Call not light faults by heauie Names; Call not all ſociable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Conuerſation, Diſloyaltie in thy Wife; Nor all leuitie, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurableneſſe, Incorrigibleneſſe in thy Sonne; nor all negligence, or forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, Perfidiouſneſſe in thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; Nor let euery light diſorder within doores, ſhut thee out of doores, or make thee a ſtranger in thine owne Houſe. In a ſmoakie roome, it may bee enough to open a Windowe, without leauing the place; In Domeſtique vnkindneſſes, and diſcontents, it may bee whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer to giue them a Concoction at home in a diſcreete patience, or to giue them a vent at home, in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate rebuke, then to thinke to eaſe them, or put them off, with falſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135873:29"/>
diuertions abroad. As <hi>States</hi> ſubſiſt in part, by keeping their weakeneſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes from being knowen, ſo is it the quiet of <hi>Families,</hi> to haue their <hi>Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie,</hi> and their <hi>Parliament</hi> within doores, and to compoſe and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all emergent differences there: for ſo alſo, <hi>Foundations</hi> beeing kept vndeſtroyed, the righteous ſhall doe, as they ſhould doe, enioy a <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Vnitie, and a <hi>Ciuill</hi> Vnitie, the ſame Soule towards <hi>God,</hi> the ſame heart towards one another, in a holy, and in a happy <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> is the <hi>foundation</hi> of this third <hi>Houſe,</hi> The <hi>Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Domus Dominus.</note>Laſtly, for thoſe things which concerne the <hi>Foundations</hi> of the fourth <hi>Houſe, Our ſelues,</hi> Miſ-interprete not <hi>Gods</hi> former Corrections vpon thee, how long, how ſharpe ſoeuer: Call not his Phiſicke, poyſon, nor his Fiſh, Scorpions, nor his Bread, Stone: Accuſe not <hi>God,</hi> for that hee
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135873:29"/>
hath done, nor ſuſpect not <hi>God,</hi> for that hee may doe, as though <hi>God</hi> had made thee, onely becauſe hee lacked a man, to damne. In all ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> ſay with Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Domine quo vadam, Lord, whither ſhall I goe, thou haſt the Word of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life,</hi> And <hi>God</hi> will not leaue thee in the darke: In all oppreſsion from potent Aduerſaries, ſay with <hi>Dauid, Tibi ſoli peccaui: Againſt thee, O Lord, onely haue I ſinned,</hi> And <hi>God</hi> will not make the malice of another man his Executioner vpon thee. Crie to him; and if hee haue not heard thee, crie lowder, and crie oftner; The firſt way that <hi>God</hi> admitted thee to him, was by VVater, the water of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme;</hi> Goe ſtill the ſame way to him, by Water, by repentant <hi>Teares:</hi> And remember ſtill, that when <hi>Ezechias</hi> wept, <hi>Vidit lachrymam, God ſaw his Teare,</hi> His Teare in the <hi>Singular; God</hi> ſawe his firſt teare, euery ſeuerall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135873:30"/>
teare: If thou thinke <hi>God</hi> haue not done ſo by thee, Continue thy teares, till thou finde hee doe. The firſt way that <hi>Chriſt</hi> came to thee, was in <hi>Blood;</hi> when hee ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the <hi>Lawe,</hi> in <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> And the laſt thing that hee bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed to thee, was his <hi>Blood,</hi> in the Inſtitution of the Bleſſed <hi>Sacrament;</hi> Refuſe not to goe to him, the ſame way too, if his glorie require that <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> If thou pray, and haſt an apprehenſion that thou heareſt <hi>God</hi> ſay, hee will not heare thy prayers, doe not beleeue that it is hee that ſpeakes; If thou canſt not chuſe but beleeue that it is hee, let mee ſay, in a pious ſenſe, doe not beleeue him: <hi>God</hi> would not bee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, in denouncing of Iudgements, ſo abſolutely, ſo peremptorily, as to bee thought to ſpeake vnconditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, illimitedly: <hi>God</hi> tooke it well at <hi>Dauids</hi> hands, that when the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:135873:30"/>
had tolde him, <hi>The childe ſhall ſurely die,</hi> yet hee beleeued not the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſo peremptorily, but that hee proceeded in Prayer to <hi>God,</hi> for the life of the childe. Say with <hi>Dauid, Thou haſt beene a ſtrong Tower to mee;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 61.4.62.7.</note> 
               <hi>I will abide in thy Tabernacle, Et non Emigrabo,</hi> I will neuer goe out, I know thou haſt a <hi>Church,</hi> I know I am in it, and I will neuer depart from it; and ſo <hi>Foundations</hi> beeing neuer deſtroyed, the righteous ſhall doe, as the righteous haue alwayes done, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the <hi>Euidence,</hi> and the <hi>Verdict,</hi> and the <hi>Iudgement,</hi> and the <hi>Poſſeſsion</hi> of a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which is the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of this fourth <hi>Houſe.</hi> Firſt, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne this firſt <hi>Houſe, Thy ſelfe,</hi> well; and as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayde, hee ſhall ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Thou haſt beene faithfull in a little, take more;</hi> Hee ſhall enlarge thee in the next Houſe, Thy <hi>Family,</hi> and the next, The <hi>State,</hi> and the other, The <hi>Church,</hi> till hee ſay to thee, as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135873:31"/>
hee did to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> after all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bleſsings, <hi>Et prosperata es in Regnum, Now I haue brought thee vp to a Kingdome,</hi> A Kingdome, where not onely no <hi>Foundations</hi> can bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, but no ſtone ſhaked; and where the Righteous know alwayes what to doe, to glorifie <hi>God,</hi> in that inceſſant Acclamation, <hi>Saluation to our God, who ſits vpon the Throne, and to the Lambe;</hi> And to this <hi>Lambe of God,</hi> who hath taken away the <hi>ſinnes</hi> of the world, and but changed the <hi>Sunnes</hi> of the world, who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated two wondrous workes in one, To make <hi>our Sunne</hi> to ſet at Noone, and to make <hi>our Sunne</hi> to riſe at Noone too, That hath giuen him <hi>Glorie,</hi> and not taken away our <hi>Peace,</hi> That hath exalted him to Vpper-roomes, and not ſhaked any <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of ours, To this <hi>Lambe of God,</hi> the glorious <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> and the moſt Almightie <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135873:31"/>
Spirit</hi> of Comfort, three Perſons, and one <hi>God,</hi> bee aſcribed by vs, and the whole <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Church,</hi> where the <hi>Father</hi> of bleſſed <hi>Memorie</hi> raignes <hi>with God,</hi> and the <hi>Militant Church,</hi> where the <hi>Sonne</hi> of bleſſed <hi>Aſſurance</hi> raignes <hi>for God,</hi> All Power, Praiſe, Might, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, Glory, and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, now, and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Errat.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Pag. 12. l. 17. for <hi>Cauſe,</hi> read <hi>Lawes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>pa 43. l. 20. for <hi>Syllagiſmus,</hi> r. <hi>Syllogiſmus.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
